<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-03-04T12:33:12+00:00</updated><id>https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Experience at the OCTOPUS Hackathon</title><link href="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/octopus-hackathon-experience-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Experience at the OCTOPUS Hackathon"/><published>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/octopus-hackathon-experience-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/octopus-hackathon-experience-2023/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/hackathon/hackathon-AI-picture.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 center" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> An illustation of the hackathon event. </div> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>The OCTOPUS hackathon occurs bi-annually and is primarily organized by the group leaders and senior researchers in Prof. Angel Rubio’s group at the Max Planck Institute for the Structure and Dynamics of Matter (MPSD) in Hamburg, Germany.</p> <p>Are you curious about what it’s like to participate in a real-space time-dependent functional theory (RT-TDDFT) code hackathon? Join me as I recount my thrilling experience and learned lessons during the 5-day OCTOPUS hackathon (February 6th-10th, 2023), where we improved and added new features to the OCTOPUS code.</p> <blockquote> <p>📘 More about OCTOPUS</p> <p><a href="https://www.octopus-code.org/documentation/12/">OCTOPUS</a> is a software package that utilizes time-dependent density functional theory to simulate electron dynamics in complex systems, including both extended and finite systems. It is written in Fortran and C++, and uses a real-space grid to solve the Khon-Sham and Maxwell equations. OCTOPUS is frequently updated and developed by a community of researchers, making it a widely used tool for exploring light-driven phenomena and quantum dynamics in molecules and materials.</p> <p>Interested? Please refer to the latest article <a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/1.5142502">“Octopus, a computational framework for exploring light-driven phenomena and quantum dynamics in extended and finite systems”</a>, N. Tancogne-Dejean et al., <em>The Journal of Chemical Physics</em> 152 124119 (2020).</p> </blockquote> <h1 id="the-hackathon-experience">The Hackathon Experience</h1> <p>The hackathon is structured as follows: on the first day, participants learn about the main tasks and who is involved in each part. Over the next few days, participants give a brief update on what they accomplished the day before, and then spend the day working to solve any issues. If someone finishes his or her task, (s)he can request more tasks from the organizers. In addition, the hackathon provides free coffee, drinks, cookies, and dinner, which is my favorite part.</p> <p>On the first day of the hackathon, one of the main organizers (Nicolas) provided a short overview of OCTOPUS and identified the main tasks and issues that needed to be resolved during the hackathon. Participants were then assigned a task, which could be changed with others if desired. These tasks were grouped and hosted by organizers with more experience in the code structure.</p> <p>I teamed up with a group leader (Hannes), an expert in solid-state materials with light-matter interactions. we swiftly narrowed our focus to three achievable projects for the 5-day hackathon: 1) implementing the Wannier interpolation method using the selected columns of the density matrix (SCDM) technique; 2) extending OCTOPUS’ SCDM method for spinors (currently only for nonspinors); and 3) computing the spread of Wannier functions with the SCDM method over time propagation. After weighing the challenges and timeframes of each project, I decided to work on the second one.</p> <p>Hannes recommended that I read <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.06958">a 2018 paper on the SCDM method</a>, as it was new to me. I spent Monday to Wednesday reading three papers on the topic - the 2018 SCDM paper, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/ct500985f">the 2017 SCDM-k paper</a>, and <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0021999116307215">the original 2015 SCDM paper</a> by the developers of the technique - and also studied the subroutines in OCTOPUS for the nonspinor version of the method implemented by Hannes.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/hackathon/reading-notes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 center" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> my notes for reading the papers and the hilights for the main equations used in the SCDM method. </div> <p>To avoid reinventing the wheel in code development, I explored the implementation of the SCDM-k method for spinors in Wannier90 (W90). I delved into the W90 subroutine to understand how the method is implemented and appreciated the detailed comments provided by its developers. As I read the papers, I sought to connect the mathematical formula to the code language used in W90. Finally, I considered how to implement the same equations in OCTOPUS, which has a different code structure than W90. Overall, it took me about two days from Tuesday afternoon to Thursday morning.</p> <p>With my background knowledge and the necessary components identified, I was ready to tackle one part of OCTOPUS (yeah, definitely create a new branch using git) and implement the SCDM-k method for spinors. I spent the last two days of the hackathon on implementing what I learned about the SCDM-k method for spinors. Surprisingly, the implementation process was not as complex as I initially anticipated. The most challenging part was understanding the programming jargon and deciphering the lines of code. In the end, I felt like a code archaeologist, excavating buried treasure and uncovering its secrets.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/hackathon/codes-snapshots.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 center" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Implementing and translaing the main ideas of what I have learned about the SCDM-k method in W90 </div> <p>In general, I felt great about being able to complete some tasks quickly. One of these tasks was new to me, and I finished it within five days. Unfortunately, there are still some problems with the program that I need to fix, as it’s causing segmentation faults. I plan to address these issues soon, possibly when I begin working on another research project that requires that feature.</p> <h1 id="the-learned-lessons">The learned lessons</h1> <blockquote> <p>🤖 <a href="https://chat.openai.com/chat">ChatGPT</a> helped me rewrite and extend this section</p> </blockquote> <p>Participating in this hackathon was a valuable learning experience for me. It gave me the opportunity to revisit and reflect upon the various stages involved in completing a code project. One of the most important stages is defining the problem statement and determining which questions or problems are worth pursuing given the time constraints. This requires a critical evaluation of the feasibility, impact, and significance of the research problem. It is essential to define clear research objectives and goals that guide the entire project.</p> <p>The next stage involves finding related resources such as research papers, websites, lectures, codes, and other materials that provide valuable insights into the problem being addressed. It is essential to learn and master the key concepts and methods involved to ensure a strong foundation for the implementation stage. This stage requires a significant investment of time and effort in reviewing, organizing, and synthesizing the relevant information.</p> <p>The implementation stage is where the rubber hits the road. It is the most challenging and time-consuming stage, where the actual coding and development of the project take place. This requires a comprehensive understanding of the problem and a strong grasp of the programming language and tools being used. Attention to detail, proper documentation, and adherence to best practices are crucial in this stage to ensure a robust and effective implementation.</p> <p>Once the implementation stage is complete, testing the implementation is the final step. This stage ensures that the implementation works as intended and meets the research objectives and goals set out in the beginning. It involves identifying and addressing any bugs or issues and verifying that the implementation meets the necessary quality and performance standards.</p> <p>In conclusion, the hackathon experience reinforced the importance of these stages in completing a successful code project and the value of careful planning, research, implementation, and testing.</p> <h1 id="what-i-would-do-differently-next-time">What I would do differently next time</h1> <p>From my experience with hackathons, there are typically two strategies that one can use. The first approach involves tackling a small and simple task that can be completed within a few hours, without the need for extensive research, before moving on to other categories or groups. For example, the OCTOPUS hackathon includes groups that focus on high performance, website design, fundamental code structure, data extraction, and output. This allows participants to work with a variety of experts specializing in fields such as DFT theory, numerical solvers, software performance, and maintenance. The second strategy involves defining a project based on a general direction, as I described earlier.</p> <p>In the future, I plan to use the first strategy to work on several small, easy tasks and learn from others. Specifically, I would like to learn how to use shell commands, how the website is constructed, how a particular time propagation solver works, and how to use git more efficiently, among other things.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal-experience"/><category term="hackathon"/><category term="coding-experience"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a participant's experience at the OCTOPUS hackathon, highlighting the challenges, rewards, and networking opportunities involved]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building a Second Brain for Personal Notes</title><link href="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/building-a-second-brain-summary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building a Second Brain for Personal Notes"/><published>2023-02-12T01:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-12T01:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/building-a-second-brain-summary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://itelu6.github.io/itelu-folio/blog/2023/building-a-second-brain-summary/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1595187139760-5cedf9ab5850?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=1531&amp;q=80" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> "The second brain is a magic kitchen for me to cook delicious foods for thoughts!" ~ I-Te Lu (the picture from <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/DcIZJsskTfg">unsplash</a>) </div> <h1 id="an-email-i-got-from-my-young-self">An email I got from my young self:</h1> <blockquote> <p>Dear I-Te (old self 🕵️),</p> <p>I would like to ask you about how you manage or orgainze your personal notes in daily life?</p> <p>You seem to have a few material ready to start with, when you kick off a project or write a manuscript.</p> <p>Could you share your strategy with me? I would like to have a systematic way to organize my notes on a wide range of topics tha I am interested in.</p> <p>Sincerely,</p> <p>I-Te (young self) 👦</p> </blockquote> <h1 id="my-response-to-the-email">My response to the email</h1> <h2 id="the-book-i-read-building-a-second-brain">The book I read “building a second brain”</h2> <p>The system I use for organizing my personal (digital) notes or project information is called “a second brain”, which I have set up when I read the book “<em>Building a Second Brain: A Proven Method to Organize Your Digital Life and Unlock Your Creative Potential</em>” by <a href="https://www.buildingasecondbrain.com/">Tiago Forte</a>. I would highly recommend you to read the book to get your own experience. However, in the following I would summarize what I have learned from that book. Alternatively, you could also use the keywords “second brain”, “note taking”, and so on on Youtube and Google to learn from others’ experience and introduction to the method.</p> <h2 id="the-purpose-of-the-second-brain">The purpose of the second brain</h2> <p>For me, the purpose of the second brain is not to have a perfect system to collect and organize all the notes, but is to have the material ready when I start to create (and then share) something such as a piece of research work, manuscript, or codes.</p> <blockquote> <p>Most important of all, don’t get caught in the trap of perfectionism</p> </blockquote> <p>The second brain is there to help us think deeperly and produce more useful information instead of consuming. As the author of the book suggests:</p> <blockquote> <p>I recommend you shift as much of your time and effort as possible from consuming to creating.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="set-up-a-second-brain">Set up a second brain</h2> <p>To set up a second brain, we need two things: 1) a container system to collect notes, called <a href="#para-the-container-to-put-notes">PARA</a>; 2) a set of principles to deal with those notes, called <a href="#code-the-principles-to-deal-with-notes">CODE</a>.</p> <h3 id="para-the-container-to-put-notes">PARA: the container to put notes</h3> <p>The container system is called <strong>PARA</strong>, which stands for:</p> <ul> <li><strong>P</strong>rojects(what I’m Working on right now): a specific and clear goal or outcome that needs to achieve</li> <li><strong>A</strong>reas (what I’m committed to over time): there is a standard (not a specific goal to reach) that I want to uphold in each of these areas such as finance or health</li> <li><strong>R</strong>esources (things I want to reference in the future): any topic I am interested in gathering information about such as quantum physics or investment</li> <li><strong>A</strong>rchives (things I’ve completed or put on hold)</li> </ul> <p>PARA can be used across a wide range of platforms where we store information and notes. For example, I have PARA systems set up on my Mac laptop, Chrome (bookmark), OneNote (electronic notebooks) and Zotero (a reference management software).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/BSB-mypara-demo.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> My PARA systems set up across different platforms. </div> <p>In additional to PARA, I personally also include a directory called “Inbox” to put any notes when I capture those notes at the first time. The first moment we capture an idea is the worst time to decide what it means and where it should go, so let’s put it into the so-called inbox and organize the note later using the CODE principles.</p> <h3 id="code-the-principles-to-deal-with-notes">CODE: the principles to deal with notes</h3> <p>The principles to organize notes is called <strong>CODE</strong> and the key concepts for each principle can be condensed into the following:</p> <ul> <li><a href="#capture-keep-what-resonates"><strong>C</strong>apture</a>: Keep What Resonates</li> <li><a href="#organize-save-for-actionability"><strong>O</strong>rganize</a>: Save for Actionability</li> <li><a href="#distill-find-the-essence"><strong>D</strong>istill</a>: Find the Essence</li> <li><a href="#express-show-your-work"><strong>E</strong>xpress</a>: Show Your Work</li> </ul> <h4 id="capture-keep-what-resonates">Capture: Keep What Resonates</h4> <p>The author of the book suggests us a method called “<a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/12-favorite-problems-how-to-spark-genius-with-the-power-of-open-questions/">Twelve favorite problems</a>” invented by a well-known physicist, Richard Feynman, to capture the information that resonates with us; the number of problems is not the main point here but gives us the starting points for what to collect.</p> <p>Ask oursevles: <strong>“what are the questions I’ve always been interested in?”</strong>. For example, some of questions that I am interested in include “How could we become very productive and learn many things quickly?”, “How does emergence work? Is there any underlying theory?”, “What is the source that the universe is accelerating?”, and so on. Once I have a clear picture on what I am interested in, I am more conscious to capture ideas from all kind of sources.</p> <p>There are four criteria proposed by the author of the book: 1) does it inspire me? 2) is it useful? 3) is it personal? 4) Is it surprising? When we read information, we could ask the above questions, and start to snapshot or capture those portions of information that resonates with us. Ideally, “no more than 10 percent of the original source, at most” suggested by the author.</p> <p>Those notes we capture should be put into the inbox; later, when we start to work on the notes, we will have a second chance to take a look at the notes, and decide where we should still keep it and then move them into our PARA systems.</p> <h4 id="organize-save-for-actionability">Organize: Save for Actionability</h4> <p>For each note in the inbox, we have to find a place of PARA for it. Aks ourselve: “<strong>How is this (note) going to help me move forward one of my current projects?</strong>”. We start at the top of PARA and moving down: In which project will this be most useful? \(\rightarrow\) No, then, in which area will this be most useful? \(\rightarrow\) No, then, which resource does this belong to? \(\rightarrow\) No, then, place in archives.</p> <p>In the projects directory, I usually have a few ongoing projects, and basically, I put all the relevant notes into the corresponding projects (for example, plese see the picture below). The number of notes for each project varies, e.g., in some projects, I have around 30+ notes, while for some, I have around 10+ nodes. Similarly, for the other PARA directories.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/BSB-project-demo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A few of my projects in the projects directory of my PARA system in my electronic notebooks. </div> <h4 id="distill-find-the-essence">Distill: Find the Essence</h4> <p>The purpose for distilling the notes is to save time for our future selves. Ask ourselves: “<strong>How can I make this (note) as useful as possible for my future self?</strong>”. Think of ourselves not just as a taker of notes, but as a giver of notes to our future selves.</p> <p>The author of the book suggests us to a method called “progressive summarization” to get the essence of the information. The method works like this: from a raw note (1st layer) to a highlighted note (2nd and 3rd layer) then to a summary note (executive summary with a few bullet points in our own words).</p> <p>For example, for preparing this article for building a second brain, when I read the book, I highlighted all the contents that resonant with me, and exported the highlighted texts into my “05_Inbox” in my OneNote. Next time (one week later) I reviewed the raw notes (1st layer), and then highlighted some of the texts in bold (2nd layer). After another one week, I reviewed and distilled down or highlighted the texts in the 2nd layer, which becomes my 3rd layer. Finally, one week after, with all the 2nd and 3rd layer highlighted texts at hand, I copied and pasted them into a blank page, and started to work on this article; notice that I do not work on anything from scratch, but with some distilled information at hand. This article is my executive summary for the book I read. One does not have to create a long executive summary like this; instead, a short summary with bullet points is good enough to serve as an executive summary for our future selves.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/itelu-folio/assets/img/BSB-progressive-summary-demo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> An example for the progressive summarization method when I prepared this article for the book. </div> <blockquote> <p>Progressive Summarization is not a method for remembering as much as possible—it is a method for forgetting as much as possible. (In the book, there is a good story on how Picasso worked on his art)</p> </blockquote> <p>A few mistakes to avoid at this stage:</p> <ul> <li>over-highlighting: each layer of highlighting should contain less than 10–20 percent of the previous layer.</li> <li>highlighting without a purpose in mind: we should do it when we are ready to create something using the note.</li> </ul> <h4 id="express-show-your-work">Express: Show Your Work</h4> <p>Here comes to the main purpose of the second brain: to create the knowledge assets. The knowledge assets can be measured in terms of the so-called intermediate packets (IPs), in additional to the final products. Five kinds of IPs we can create and reuse in our work are distilled notes, outtakes, work-in-process, final deliverables, and documents created by others. Ask ourselves the following questions: “<strong>What are the knowledge assets you’re creating today that will be most reusable in the future?What are the building blocks that will move forward your projects tomorrow?</strong>” For example, my 1st, 2nd and 3rd layer notes (shown in the previous section) or the executive summary for this article.</p> <p>After I learn this principle from the book, now everyday when I start working on my research projects, I always ask myself the following question: <em>what is the intermediate packet I can produce/provide after today’s work or research exploration?</em> For example, when reading a scientific paper, my IP is usually a short summary on the paper, where I list a few bullet points for the key concepts or what I need to know (what resonate with me); For working on formula derivation, I usually end up an IP, which can be a derivation note or a summary of a few insights during the derivation; when implementing a few equations in an open source code, my IP is the git log or commit to show what I have done; for writing a manuscript, my IP can be an outline, a section, or a few paragraphs for describing a concept.</p> <p>The most important step after I finish my IP is to inform my colleagues of what I have done in the project or to send out the IP to my colleagues for a quick feedback.</p> <blockquote> <p>Reframing your productivity in terms of Intermediate Packets (IPs) is a major step toward this turning point. It’s about taking ownership of your work, your ideas, and your potential to contribute in whatever arena you find yourself in.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="tips-for-working-on-a-project">Tips for working on a project</h2> <p>When we work on a project, the process can be roughly categorized into two modes: divergence and convergence. The two modes are not a linear path but a loop. In the divergence mode, we open and explore every possible option, searching online and jumping from one to another page, capturing all sorts of the relevant notes. On the other mode, convergence mode, we turn off all the distractions including searching more information, and trust our notes and create the intermediate products or the final product toward completion.</p> <p>The temptation for searching more information for our project, when we decide to work in the convergence mode, seem to be forward progress and productive; however, it in fact postpones the moment of completion. When working in the convergence mode, we should pay attention to that temptation. One way I find useful to overcome the temptation is to simply write down what to search into another sticky note, which sends a signal to my brain that I will do it later once I am working in the divergence mode but not now.</p> <blockquote> <p>Overcome the fear of missing out. Note that we are not completing the whole project at one sitting; our aim is to complete the small intermediate packet.</p> </blockquote> <p>The author of the book suggests three methods for us when we work in the convergence mode:</p> <ol> <li>the Archipelago of Ideas (give ourselves stepping-stones): I usually put all the related notes on a blank page and start with those notes, so not from the scratch.</li> <li>the Hemingway Bridge (use yesterday’s momentum today): “Stop when you are going good” suggested by Hemingway. What I usally do is to write down the current status, any details we have in mind, and the intention for the next work session.</li> <li>Dial down the scope (ship something small and concrete): ask ourselves “What is the smallest version of this I can produce to get useful feedback from others?”</li> </ol> <h2 id="final-words">Final words</h2> <p>Above I have mentioned the key ideas of building up a second brain via the PARA system and the CODE principles. I wish you enjoy building your second brain and exploring the system by yourselve. I believe that, after experiencing how to deal with notes via the second brain system, you will become more confident and successful in swimming in the overwhelming information sea, and start to work on your projects with the intermediate packets in mind.</p> <p>P.S. If you are interested in more details on how to set up a second brain, please refer to the book that I mentioned at the beginning. Here I do not mention a few sections in the book inclduing the relevant habits for maintaining the second brain and how to reflect on the system and the notes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-summary"/><category term="notetaking"/><category term="tips-for-students"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the summary for the book "Buidling a Second Brain" by Tiago Forte]]></summary></entry></feed>